[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
we're going to plunge deeply deeply
deeply into the hamiltonian method of qu
of mechanics not Quant
mechanics we've studied the leian method
we've studied the principle of least
action we've even gone to the extremely
Advanced study of Newton's
equations um
tonight is Hamilton's
night part of the point in fact maybe
the main point of the hamiltonian
formulation of mechanics goes back to
something that I talked about at the
very first
lecture we talked about basic structure
of classical thinking classical
mechanics but not classical mechanics
quite but something even a little more
primitive we talked about discret
systems the coin which could either be
heads no this way is heads heads or
tails and that's a two-state system two
simple States and then we talked about
possible laws of evolution one simple
law of evolution is nothing happen
Evolution now might mean a sequence of
States uh separated by a small time
interval a discret time interval a 10th
of a second or whatever we update every
tenth of a second then we spoke about a
simple law of nature was which was a
simple law of coin flipping or coin
changing which would be no change at all
it's here and it's here and it's here
without doing anything that's a simple
law of uh of
um Evolution another less simple law of
evolution is if it heads then the next
time it's Tails if it's tails the next
time it's
heads Tails heads Tails heads Tails
heads both of these rules have a feature
that if you know the state of the system
at any instant of time you know it at
the next instant of time
in other words the updating rule is
precise but also the backdating rule is
also precise if you know where you are
in any instant you know where you
were we even talked about the general
structure of such simple theories
instead of just two states we could
imagine a system with many states each
one being represented by a point in a
space we might as well now call that
space phase
space it's the phase space of a simple
discrete system in this case it's got 1
2 3 4 5 6 if I stop there with only six
states then we could be talking about a
Dy a Dy is in dice six possible
configurations uh add two more I don't
know we could be talking what what
system has eight states
three pennies three
coins three
coins
um
precisely
so this is a general kind of
situation and the basic setup in fact
the definition of a phase space is if
you know where you are in the face space
you know where you'll be next and you
know where you came from
so there a rule which could be
represented simply by a set of arrows
which tells you where to go
next oh nope you can't come back because
you've already been
there here here here here and then back
to Here For example you can have other
kinds of
laws not different in uh in kind but
different in detail for example you
could have some closed loops like
this so wherever you are you go to the
next place but now there's some closed
sort of
Cycles uh so that if you're on this
cycle you will stay there and if you're
on this cycle you will stay there this
corresponds to the existence of a
conservation law we can imagine that
this these three states over here are
labeled as having
property equal to + one and over here
property the same property is minus one
well if You' got + one you stay + one +
one never becomes minus1 and minus one
never becomes + one because all of the
configurations with number minus one go
to configurations with number minus one
and so forth but
both of these kinds of laws have the
property that if you know where you are
you know where you'll be and you know
where you were that's to be contrasted
with a
law
which might look something like this if
you're over here you go to here if
you're over here you go to here and if
you're over here you go to
here that's a very definite updating
rule wherever you are you know where to
go next
but there's something funny about it
namely in particular you can't go
backward in the unique in a unique way
you can go backward from this point from
this point you know that you must have
come from here but if you're over here
you don't know whether you came from
here or whether you came from
here what's going on here is points are
running into each
other there's yet another way to think
of it imagine the phase space being
populated populated with uh
points and the point in fact let's
imagine the entire phase space is
populated with red
dots and the red dots all move they do a
dance the dance is simply to follow the
trajectories uh as they're prescribed by
the Law whatever the law is so this red
dot goes to here this red dot goes to
here this red dot goes to here this red
dot goes to
here no every Red Dot knows where to go
knows where to come
from and there's a kind of um rigidity
to the red B to the red dots none
disappear none
spontaneously appear none disappear none
appear they simply just
rigidly or um what's an even better word
than
rigidly uh a fluid incompressible kind
of incompressible motion where points
don't run into each other same thing
here same thing here if we populate the
points with red dots and we allow them
to
move along the arrows Instant by Instant
by instant each instant the number of
red dots is the same they don't run into
each other they don't bifurcate the
whole thing just moves in an
incompressible way on the other hand
with this law we could start a red
point at each
place but then after one
motion this one would have disappeared
never to
reappear and we would have only two
places which were occupied
going back and forth back and forth
there would be some loss in a sense of
points in the phas
space phas space points would not be
conserved the whole point of Hamilton's
mechanics Hamilton's form of mechanics
is number one it's a form in which every
Point knows where to go next and knows
where came from without points ever
being lost or
gained in other words a kind of rigid
motion in a phas space on incompressible
motion of the points in Phase
space uh which may also be called
information
conservation we'll see we'll we'll talk
about that a little bit further in the
future okay another point of ham
equations let's let's think about
ordinary FAL ma type equations they're
not of this form why
not well let's suppose you know where
you are let's make a
plot here's the positions of a particle
possible positions of a
particle here's the particle X Y and
Z supposing I know the particle is over
here do I know know where it will be
next no I need to know something else I
need to know not only where it is now
but I need to know where it was in
instant back in other words I mean to
know the position and the velocity
knowing the position and the velocity is
the same thing as knowing the position
in an instant and knowing the position a
slight bit earlier so I need two pieces
of information I need to know where the
object is and I also need a kind of
ghost piece of information which is
where it was an instant
ago and that's enough to tell me where
it will be
next next means after a short prescribed
period of
time
so specifying the locations of a system
by now we can simply call them the cues
of a system does not constitute a phase
space the phase space con constitutes
everything you need to
know in order to tell where you be
next but in such a way that there's a
rigidity to the
motion a rigidity to the motion points
never gained or lost that's what phase
space is Phase space is a way of
representing the configurations of a
mechanical
system uh so
that the Motions are
described much as I described these
discreet discreet motions we'll come
back to it in detail may ask a question
here before we move on yeah and um I
wonder if you can talk about what some
of the insights or pressures or
motivations were for this reformulation
of Newtonian mechanics uh
well yeah I think the lran formulation
was formulated by people for practical
reasons the Practical reasons being most
systems were awfully complicated and
difficult to apply f equals
m and so a more General a more General
formulation which was not dependent on
particular sets of coordinates in many
many
contexts recti linear coordinates are
simply not appropriate to a problem
components of vectors are not
appropriate to a problem were not
particularly useful uh motion for
example motion of a particle on the flat
Blackboard can be nicely described by
x's and y's and we can use X and Y
components and write FAL ma motion on
the surface of a
sphere an object moving around on a
surface of a sphere it's not natural in
any special sense to introduce
rectangular coordinates you can't
introduce rectangular coordinates onto
the sphere here you can introduce
coordinates latitude and longitude but
you can introduce rectangular
coordinates and the naive idea of um
components the naive idea of components
rectangular cartisian coordinates is not
useful so it's more it's useful to
Define mechanics in a way that doesn't
depend on any specific Co set of
coordinates that was the that was lr's
Mo
motivation what Hamilton was smoking I
don't
know but what he developed was an
extremely beautiful
elegant formulation of mechanics which
turned out which I I don't think he ever
really used for anything he simply
admired it and uh physicist admired it
afterwards it turned out to be very
useful part of of the usefulness of it
was because it does conserve information
in the same sense that I described over
here I'm sure he was aware of that but I
don't know if it was foremost in his
mind but ultimately the real power of it
came when quantum mechanics was
developed so
um it's hard for me to put myself in
Hamilton's position I mean it was one of
these brilliant mathematical
insights that kind of came from nowhere
just
uh uh somehow he saw the structures
there in ways that I think most of us
would not have and so no I can't really
give you his intuitions what we can do
is do it and after we've done it go out
back and talk about why it's so useful
and why it uh why it's of such power I'm
not particularly sure that anybody
realized how powerful and useful it
was um um until quantum mechanics was
developed I think that really was the
time when people first really began
feeling they had to learn what Hamilton
had had to say because he was long dead
by that
time all right another way another
observation about
it is it takes a certain number of
second order differential
equations FAL ma is a second order
differential equation for each component
second order means that it involves
second
derivatives not first derivatives but
second derivatives so it may also
involve a first derivative here and
there but it contains second
derivatives it contains accelerations
second derivatives with respect to time
of something how many equations are
there well if there are a certain number
of
particles in a certain number of
Dimensions that tells you how many
equations there are one particle there
are three equations two particles there
are six equations and so forth each one
being a second order differential
equation what H what what Hamilton's
equations or in general you can always
take a system of second order
differential equations let's say n of
them and replace them by twice as many
first order equations that only contain
first
derivatives it's very easy it's so easy
it's almost stupid so let's uh let's
discuss how you take
in second order
equations method is completely General
but I'll just illustrate it for uh for
Newton's equations supposing we have a
certain number of equations of the form
derivative second derivative of some I
component of x
by DT
^2 is equal to the I component of force
divided by the mass I've written
acceleration is equal to f m I don't
know why exactly I just wanted to write
the acceleration on the left hand side
let's suppose now that there are in such
differential
equations let's take that and make two n
equations Each of which only contains a
first time derivative
to do that first of all
Define now we can do it in many ways but
I'm going to do it in a particular way
that uh that'll be uh in order to get
familiar with the
terminology first of all let's re let's
define d XI by
DT and and let's throw in a factor of
the mass the mass of the
I that's one Mass everybody has the same
mass
let's take M * d x DT and give it a name
what do we call it we call it P
sub now let's
write I don't know why I put M on the
left hand on the right hand side of the
equation what did I do that let's put it
backward along FAL ma now let's write
FAL ma in the form h m ah let's just
make one m
all right now let's take uh this is of
course A first order equation it only
contains first time derivatives but now
let's write FAL ma a in the form DP by
DT isal to f i
i both of these equations are only first
order
equations but there are twice as many of
them there are twice as many equations
but each one only containing first time
derivatives they become a twoin a system
of twoin differential equations for
twice as many variables and now what are
the what are the twice as many variables
x sub I and P of
I first order equations are the kind
which tell you where to go if you know
where you are without knowing where you
were a first order equation tells you
how to update to the next position if
you know where you are but knowing where
you are now means knowing where you are
in the phase space it's equivalent to
the old view you again need to know two
things a position and something
equivalent to a velocity but it's just a
different uh
mindset thinking about the phase
space gives you a picture X and P in
which wherever you are you know where to
go
next so there's no new physics in it no
new laws of nature just a different
mindset thinking about the state of a
system not as a
configuration but as a combination of a
position and a momentum or not just one
position and momentum but a position and
a momentum for each degree of freedom
for each coordinate
more generally of course we would talk
about q's and P's or q's and pies I
think I'm going to give up the notation
Pi I got the uh we is call canonical
momentum P will be done with
it but those are the various
um motivations various properties of the
hamiltonian description it's the
equation of it's hamiltonian description
of mechanics is the equations for how
things move around on a phase space
knowing where you are they tell you
where you move next in fact you can
almost think of it just as I eras yeah I
did we had but let's put it back
we thought of a law as being a kind of
flow a flow of the points in Phase
space we're going to see that there's a
natural sense in which mechanics
constitutes a flow in the phase space
wherever you are you know where to go
next and if you were to imagine a
populating the phase space populating
the phase space would mean taking a lot
of identical systems and starting each
one at a different point in the phase
space and watching them as they evolve
that would define a flow in this phase
space and it's that flow in the phase
space that h mechanics is all
about it's almost as if the points in
Phase space were kind of fluid and we're
studying how that fluid moves if we're
interested in any specific system then
we think of it as a little particle
moving along with the flow we start at
someplace we allow it to move along with
the flow and uh follow its coordinates
and
momentum all right now we need a small
piece of mathematics it's an easy piece
of mathematics or it's a rather formal
piece it's so mathematics it's called
the wandra
transformation we going do it first in
the simplest possible
case Suppose there are two variables let
me call them V and
P just secretly between you and me v
stands for velocity and P stands for
momentum
but now forget I told you that because
we're going to think about the Leandra
transformation as a mathematical trick
in many many different
contexts all right so I have there are
two
variables and let's suppose whoops p is
V and P but they're not independent
variables in fact there's really only
one variable they're functions of each
other they're functions of each other
and for Simplicity not for Simplicity
this is important let's suppose there's
single valued functions of each other
single valued function means that if you
know P you know V and if you know V you
know p no
ambiguity that means the graph of P
versus
V looks something like that what it
can't do is it's not allowed to do that
why not because if it did this there
would be certain values of P where you
would have an ambiguity about what V
is it's also not allowed to do this
because then there would be certain
values of V where you wouldn't know what
P
was single valued means that the graph
of the function function P versus V
looks like this any point on
it or for any value of
V there's a unique p and for any value
of P there's a unique
V actually just for Simplicity although
this this is not important let's just
draw the graph so that it goes to the
arig
then if we have such a single valued
function not just a single valued
function but a one to one
function meaning it's single valued
whether you think about it as p as a
function of v or V is a function of P
then it's possible to invent a pair of
functions one which I'll call
L
secretly the
lran and the lran is a function of
v and it has the property that the
derivative of the
lran with respect to
V defines
P why would I bother inventing a
function
l whose derivative with respect to V is
p well come to Y but I can always do it
uh this is just ordinary derivative for
the moment since there's only one
variable V we don't have to make it a
partial
derivative
d l by
DV we're going to find
that given l
we can construct a symmetrically related
function that we're going to call
H H is to be regarded as a function of
P when we think about L we will think
about v as the independent variable when
we think about H we will think about p
as the independent variable of course L
is also a function of P because V is a
function of P of course H is also a
function of v because p is a function of
v
so uh but each one is thought of as a
function of its own variable L of V or h
of p and the relationship is H and L are
connected
by the derivative of H with respect to P
is
B this is a completely symmetrical
relation between p and v and between l
and H
the derivative with respect to V of L is
p the derivative of P of H is V now let
me show you why that's always possible
to do and to show you the relationship
between l and
H okay
let's let's take our function which the
Simplicity I just had passed through the
origin but you can work it out whether
it passes through the origin or
not notice the derivative of L with
respect to V is equal to P think of that
as p as a function of v of course V is
the independent variable in the top
equation so p is really a function of v
as it is over here P of V remember the p
is a function of I just it over here P
of
V we can also think of V is a function
of T and
now let's solve this equation for L by
just writing that
L is equal to the
integral of P of V
DV does everybody recognize that if the
derivative of
L is p then L is the integral of
P
we can write this as D does everybody
recognize what I've done
here okay that can be taken to be a
definite integral and for definit let's
take it to be the integral from zero but
it doesn't
matter it doesn't matter where we take
the integral from but let's for definit
take it from zero from V equal
Z if we differentiate an integral we
just get the integram so if we
differentiate L with respect to let's
put V up here definitely integral from 0
to
V here
vdv if you differentiate an integral
with respect to the end point of
integration you just get the integram so
that's this relationship here derivative
of L is equal to P we can always do this
here that's L of the end point if you
like
all right we can now draw a picture of
what l
means at least on this graph L is the
area L of
V or let's say l of V is constructed in
the following
way you go to a point
V you
draw that line and then you consider all
the
area underneath the curve here
this is not a triangle it's a
curve that's the integral of P of V DV
and it's the L at Point
v l of
v it has the property that if you
differentiate it with respect to V you
get
P now what about H well we can do the
same thing with
h h must be the integral of V DP just by
symmetry the
uh the other equation is the H of
p is the integral we can again start at
zero and go to
P of V of P
DP notice that if we differentiate H
with respect to P we just get
V that's the other defining equation
have derivative of H with respect to P
is equal to
V all right so the geometry of that then
is
[Applause]
that
H the area in here is H H of p and the
area in here is L of
V this is this area in here is the
integral of V of of
pp do that me further
explanation
well now we know the relationship
between H and
L take the take H and add it to L H+
L is the area of this whole
rectangle what's the area of the
rectangle it's p *
V this is usually
written as H is equal to PV minus L but
it's clearly the same
thing for some reason we tend to write
we tend to think of L first and then try
to figure out what H is
all right so now let's write our system
of
equations they called aandre
transformation you start with an L of
V you differentiate L of
V ordinary derivative we do
here derivative of L with respect to
V defines
p and it gives you p as a function of
B then you
construct
H by multiplying P * B and subtracting
L now L of course is a function of v but
wherever you see
V substitute its value in terms of P so
we're can to think of this as L same
scrip L of V but V is a function of
P so V is also a function of P here so H
gets to be thought of as a function of
p l is a function of
v and when we do this we'll now prove
I'll now prove although it's it's clear
from the geometry here that the
derivative of H with respect to P is
V let's do the little manipul
algebraically here's what we do we
consider a small change of p and ask how
much H
changes how much does H change when we
change P let's work it
out the change in h let's just call it
Delta H Small Change in h is first of
all what's the change in a
product if we change a if we make a
small change in the values of some
variables what's the change in a
product sum of two terms the sum of two
terms one term being the first Factor
times the change in the second and vice
versa all right so first of all we get a
term which is p times the small change
in V the second term is V plus the small
change in
p and finally
minus the derivative of the Lan
derivative of L with respect to
V remember that L depends only on V
times the change in
V but wait a minute I defined DL by DV
to be called P that was the way that I
constructed P from l
d l by DV is equal to P so look right
here we have d l by DV I'm sorry I
sometimes write partial derivatives and
sometimes total it doesn't matter and
there's only one variable partial and
total are the same all right so this
thing
is
p well here I have pdv here I have minus
pdv so these two cancel
completely these two are the same and
therefore
cancel not the same but opposite and
that just
leaves the change in h is V * the change
in
P that's the same thing as saying that d
h by
DP is equal to
V the H by DP is equal to V in other
words the change in h when I change p a
little bit is is just equal to
V okay that is the Leandra
transformation so L to find the LDV to
be
P then construct H which is PV minus L
and now you have a reciprocal
relationship where D H by DP is equal to
V so if we interchange L and we
interchange l and H and we also
interchange p and v it's completely
symmetric they're completely
symmetrically related to each other this
little demonstration over here is
nothing
but uh the geometry of that rectangle
being divided H and
L that's a mathematical construction
which is not only which is at the heart
of many many
things particular
mechanics but also
thermodynamics thermodynamics is just
filled with Leander Transformations all
over the place and
variables are related in
pairs uh pairs now what happens if there
are many V's instead of just one V
supposing there are many of
them then the definitions go as follows
the derivative of L with respect to the
i
v is the i p just keep you should Pro
probably remember what V is V is some
velocity and in hamiltonian sorry Lan
mechanics keep in mind that the
derivative of a lran with respect to a
velocity is a
momentum this is just all right let's
let's uh let's apply this toan mechanics
in a few minutes but this is not a new
relationship for us now of course we
should use partial derivatives because
I'm imagining many variables
partial of L with respect
to that's piece ofi definition at this
point now we construct h of P not of a
single momentum but of a collection of
PS h of p mean h of all of the peas and
this
becomes some over all of the I's P sub i
v sub
IUS
L this may start to look familiar to
you let's go through the
same little derivation
here
now the change in H is a sum of
patterns a pie of i v of I I'm not going
to write summation signs whenever I
write a pie of I and V of ey like that
and so forth think some over the
eyes all right so first of all a piece
of I Delta P of I a v subi Delta P sub I
and then a derivative of L with respect
to V subi * Delta
V when I change things a little bit this
is what happens to H
again exactly the same pattern d l by
DVI is the same as P subi so they cancel
the things inside R cancel and all I'm
left with is that the change in
h is equal to the
i v variable times the
change in the i p
variable from this you could easily read
off that the derivative of H the partial
derivative of H with respect to P sub I
is equal to V sub I in other words the
change in h if you only change one of
the
PS let's say the third P the change in h
if you change p sub3 a little bit is
just V sub3 keeping all the other PS
fixed so the derivative of H respect the
P sub I is just V
subi okay so again same kind of
reciprocity the L by the V subi is p
subi the H by the p subi is V subi
completely symmetrically related to each
other now at the moment these are just
abstract
variables sometimes I've called one of
them a momentum sometimes I've called
one of them a
velocity uh but they could be just
abstract variables
and as I said there are many
applications of the change of variables
from a vtype variable to a ptype
variable that's kept track of by what
I'm usually call generating functions l
and
H all right but our interest is in
mechanics in mechanic the Lan is not
only a function of velocities it's also
a function of
positions we haven't talked about
positions at all we have velocities here
or things I called V and we have things
I called
P the relationship between P's and v's
and lonians and hamiltonians is exactly
what I've written but with the
coordinates Q just going along for the
ride just going along as if they as if
you didn't care about them as if they
were just passive so let me show you how
the relationship between hamiltonians
and Lans is nothing but a LeAndre
transformation of exactly this
type with the extra added ingredient
that there's some more variables that go
along for the
r all right now we're doing mechanics we
have a
l
lran is a function of what it's a
function of the Q
dots but let's call the Q dots
V's velocity generalized velocity V subi
Q subi do is by definition V subi so
then the Lan is a function of the v's
and the
q's don't confuse Q's with
[Applause]
p's
B sub I is equal to Q dot let me write
up here another equation of mechanics
that you're familiar with p subi is the
derivative of the lran with respect to Q
dot remember
that DL byq dot defines P but that's the
same as saying DL by
DV
uhhuh d l by
DV equals pie of
I that's the first of our equations over
here so we start to
see uh the Leandra transformation
between P's and velocities beginning to
shape up and it's simply the it's simply
the definition of canonical momentum
as the derivative of leian with respect
to
Q next let's define the
hamiltonian I'm absolutely repeating
myself now but I'm repeating myself in
the language of mechanics let's define
the hamiltonian H to be the
sum of p
subi p ofi what p ofi
V
subi usually we write p subi q subi dot
right that's the language that we've
done previously but Qi thought is
nothing but V subi so let's put V
subi minus
logian that's precisely the same
definition that we had for the Honan I
think in the last two lectures so you
see we see the pattern shaping up but
now now let's calculate the small change
in h when we change things what things
we're going to change the P's and the
q's what happens if we make small
changes in p's and
q's how does the hamiltonian change
let's calculate that you you're taking
the velocity to
be a function of p and Q it is a
function gend transformation generally
that's right in general you can think of
Q as just going along as a for a ride as
a set of parameters okay right velocity
depends on but yeah the whole thing yeah
that's right so that's correct now okay
what was said was was correct let me
rephr not rephrase it but let me just
restate
it now the relationship between the P's
and the
v's is such that P
is a function not just of V but also the
q's and V is a function of the P's and
the q's but you can simply think of the
q's as being parameters at this
point uh which
uh as I said go along for the ride for
the
moment the point is of course when you
calculate d l by d v sub I in general it
might contain some C dependence and not
just the dependence but that's
okay just uh just pursue it okay let's
calculate the change in h when you
change things a little bit change things
means change everything a little bit p's
and
q's all right the change in
ag same thing as before is first of all
the sum which I won't write the
summation sign P
subi Delta V subi
V subi Delta p
subi and now I have minus the derivative
of the
lran have two things that the lran
depends on see which way the L by Q
subi Delta q
subi
and
minus d
l by the V
subi Delta V
subi Grans depend on q's and
v's and now we're varying everything in
sight p's and q's you don't have to
separately vary the velocities because
you know the velocities if you know the
p's and
q's okay so there we are that's the
formula for changing h a little bit it
has several terms P subi Delta
Deli derivative of Lan with respect to Q
time a changing Q derivative Lan with
respect to V Delta
V okay it's a little bit complicated but
fortunately big pieces of it just
cancel just as it did over here in fact
the same R cancellation takes place over
here remember that the L by the VAB body
is pie of
body here's pie of here's pie of
body things in the red squares cancel
again they're
gone the other two terms can't cancel
each other one involves Delta P the
other involves Delta Q those are
independent variations they can't cancel
each other but what we can write down
now is that the derivative of the
hamiltonian with respect to pie
ofi that's a small change in h when you
change pie ofi a little
bit keeping Q subi
fixed the H by the P ofi keeping the q's
fixed is just one what do you read off
this
visi and the H by d q subi what's
that
that's this is
minus
DL by DQ
subi so far okay that's not bad it's
nice equations but they get a little bit
nicer L by
B L by b v right well no sorry the L by
the QI right that's
it you remember the lanes equations d l
by the Q subi what's
that okay let's write Down's equations
over
here D by
DT of DL by DQ
sub
dot is equal to D L by DQ sub
I
that's what gr's
equations what's the L by the
q p so this is the left hand side is p
do I is equal
L that's all it says that the time
derivative of the canonical momentum is
DL by
DQ well let's look at what we have here
we have DL like a q
right that's just
equal the minus
P that's look around just
equations P dot is d by
DQ so we have one equation let's get rid
of the middleman here we don't need them
the H by
DQ is minus the time derivative of
P what is
i
q I'm going to go through this
again I'm going to do it again oh these
of course are Hamilton's
equations they're quite
beautiful H is a function of p's and
q's that's the way you think about it
the hamiltonian is a function of p's and
q's momenta and coordinates you get rid
of the velocities replace them by P's
and then the derivative of the
hamiltonian with respect to P's defines
the Q dots and the derivative of the
hamiltonian with respect to Q's is minus
the P
dots that's the structure of
mechanics in the hamiltonian nutshell if
you
like
let's go through it again just uh since
it was a a series of steps all of which
are abstract none of which are entirely
intuitive let's go through it again here
we have
H is
equal
summation P sub i v sub
I Min -
l l being a function of Q and V
now let's make a little
variation that's going to equal p sub I
Delta v
subi v subi Delta P
subi
minus the change in
L Del what's that oh sorry excuse me
thank
youus V
Delta but now we have to calculate the
change in
L the change in L is minus the
derivative of L with respect to whatever
it depends on but it depends on
Q's Del q's and it depends on
V's everybody gets an
odd and there should be a summation sign
which I'm to Lazy
right okay now first of all what cancels
the things multiplying Delta V cancel
why here you have piece of
I and here sorry did I say that right
yes yeah
um
yeah the L by V sub I that's P sub I
definition of p sub I the L
by that's how we def canonical
momentum gone
gone and then we look at left what's
left over and we see that the derivative
of H with respect to pie of I is V subi
but V subi is Q
do
and then we look at the other one that
says the derivative of H with respect to
Q sub
I is equal to minus d l by Q sub
IUS but then we use Lan's
equations d l by DQ
subi is d by
DT of P ofi let's equation or or just
minus P
dot so we see that
mechanics in great
generality gets
repackaged as a system of first order
equations of very great Simplicity you
need to know one function of PS and q's
knowing our function of p's and q's
immediately by
differentiation tells you
how the point moves through phase space
it tells you the velocity through phase
space Q dot of course is just the
ordinary velocity but the combination Q
Dot and P dot let's put the sign on the
other side over
here the combination Q Dot and P dot is
a kind of velocity through the phase
space it tells you if you know p and Q
you plug it in the h calcul the HTP the
hdq if you know p and Q then you
immediately know P Dot and Q
dot so it reduces mechanics to the
system of first order equations for p's
and q's every P has a partner called Q
every Q has a partner called P they come
in come in
pairs and the Hamilton equations
[Music]
are one sorry two for each i a pair of
equations for each
R let's do it just for Simplicity for uh
for FAL ma let's just check that it
really is
correct FAL
ma as I said I have no idea what M
motivated uh Hamilton to write
down but they certainly do have a very
very simple structure and one of the
things I show you is that surprisingly
with very very different physical
interpretation p's and q's seem to be
very very different
things Q's are coordinates P's are
velocities are connected to velocities
and yet there's this enormous symmetry
between p's and q's they seem to come
into the equations in an extremely
parallel and symmetric way apart from a
single minus sign over
here they seem to enter in
uh in a symmetric way into
mechanics and it's the study of these
equations which really uh defines modern
mechanics if you like modern uh
classical
mechanics
let's draw a picture to indicate what's
going
on here's General phase space p and
Q there not just one variable there's
many
variables some subset are called P's
half of them are called P's half of them
are called Q's I can't draw them all on
the Blackboard so I'll draw just one p
and one
Q at every
Point where's my equations here they are
at every point I could calculate the H
by the p and the H by theq and tell you
exactly what Q do and P do are that
defines a kind of velocity Vector
through the uh through the phase space
not an ordinary velocity but a phase
space velocity let's draw that phase
space velocity as an arrow it's showing
which way that point is moving in the
phase space and the length of the arrow
we can take to rep ENT how fast you're
moving through the phas
space and so what the hamiltonian gives
you is a a kind of flow through the face
space where the arrows are long you're
moving fast where the arrows
are small you move
slowly and the velocity as I said is
related related to derivatives notice
one funny thing that the Q velocity is a
p derivative and the P velocity is minus
a q
derivative okay so it's not that Q dot
is the derivative of H with respect to q
and P Do Is Der the H with respect to P
they get crossed here they get crossed
in the equation that has a profound
implication as we'll see in a
moment any questions about Hamilton's
equations up to
now any any second order system any
second order system can always
be just by defining the first
derivatives to be new
variables then that simply defines a set
of twice as many uh first letter
equations that's trivial but uh this
elegant structure here is far more than
that it has some properties that we'll
see in a
moment yeah um are there any systems
where p and B are not one to one
relationships um when it happens they
usually badly Define systems for which
the um the evolution is not well defined
and usually rejected as being you mean
are there any systems in nature which
require circular systems with
with friction doesn't that be slowly
well first of all friction is outside
the boundaries of uh of
uh
of the bran and hamiltonian mechanics
okay now not really because uh all
systems in nature are of this type and
friction is a part of nature but as I
emphasized over and over again you don't
really see friction in the system
unless you ignore a large large number
of
coordinates uh friction is the simply
the excitation and the moving around of
microscopic coordinates that you don't
keep track of
so yeah the let me see I'm trying to
think are there any systems that I can
think
of where you can't invert the relation
between coordinates and
momenta yeah I can think of one
no I can't think of sorry no I can't
think of any uh off hand that make
physical
sense we'll talk about why and we'll
talk about the importance of this one
one how about the falling at terminal
velocity what no that's
friction that's friction what's
happening is uh is is right you can
cannot write equations with friction in
this
form friction outside the boundaries of
formulation in the sense that if you
wrote the equations that you normally
write down for friction they won't be of
this form if you write the equations
governing all of the molecules every
single one of them and keep track of
them all then there's simply a huge
number of equations which do have this
form so introducing friction is a way of
approximating a very very large number
of equations of this
form uh by a very small number of
equations and ignoring the motion of
most of the degrees of freedom energy is
leaking off into other degrees of
freedom so friction we don't want to
deal with now friction is exceedingly
complicated if we Define H as that lower
left hand corner yes and then take Delta
H and we apply
U the the oil of the garage equations
then we get these equations that's
correct okay now but that's but where is
this Leandra thing coming in here I mean
what I I me well here we we did D L by
DV is
p and d h by
the here this is the Lungi
transformation
what is the is it the equation is it the
the right hand side is
it it's taking a f it's taking a
function of
v what is it it's a
procedure it's a procedure of changing
variables if you like changing variables
from a set called V to a set called p is
there any way you could describe that in
words I mean I can sort of follow the
the arithmetic
transformation is a whole bunch of
arithmetic that goes into
it well you can go from X to U or you
know anything like
that if you like to me this is the
clearest uh definition of what you're
doing you have a pair of variables V and
P they're connected to each other if
they're connected in a one to one way
then you can Define you can define an l
ofv and an H of
L of V is the integral under this curve
out to some v h of p is the integral
over this curve up to
P the derivative of L with respect to
V is p and the derivative of H with
respect to P is
v p * V is L + H that's the simple
geomet of it why is it so
useful um you get used to it and you uh
you do it over and over again and you
begin to see why it's useful but
uh let I would suggest we just go with
it and we will find out just how useful
Hamilton's equations are yeah so you
that single value which one yeah what
happens it's single value then you have
a bad system then you have a system
which uh physics
uh well it usually means the equations
of motion break down at some point
uh uh some breakdown in the predictivity
of the equations some Singularity
happens
sit they are oh
okay we could we could write down some
lonians and hamiltonians which are bad
and try to see why they're bad I think
that's a that's a good thing to do I'm
not going to do it tonight some somebody
send me an email just send me an email
saying write down some bad systems and
we'll write down some examples where
things don't work out well and try to
follow them and see where the motion
breaks down see what happens to the
motion how it tells you all of a sudden
you don't know which way to
go uh it usually means at some point the
equation of motion simply is singular
there's some Infinity in it and uh
something breaks down that doesn't tell
you where to go something in the
equation becomes infinite as a general
rule it means that your physics is wrong
at some point I think it us it always
means your physics is wrong
yeah uh I know at least one example
where it means uh something uh can
travel with infinite velocity all kinds
of things can go wrong but I think it's
a good idea to take an example or two
which where you cannot invert the
relationship between velocity and
momentum and see exactly what goes wrong
and I will do that for you if you send
me an email message you can do it kind
of a strange question um why is it okay
to have an infinite number of degrees of
freedom in quantum mechanics when we're
frightened of many degrees of freedom in
friction
um no it's
not well first of all we can have an
infinite number of degrees of freedom in
classical
mechanics infinite doesn't have to do
with the difference between quantum
mechanics and classical mechanics a
field has an infinite number of degrees
of
freedom right are we frightened of it uh
it can get pretty
frightening uh having a field can Le the
friction for
example a
electron accelerating radiates it
radiates photons the radiation of those
photons tend to act like a kind of
friction and it can get very very
complicated to follow the motion of an
electron including radiation reaction
and so forth um why are we afraid we're
not afraid of the many degrees Freedom
we just have to remember that they're
there I think you're asking why it's so
terribly difficult to to derive the laws
of friction and the laws of mechanics
well that is hard but it's also hard to
derive the laws of radiation
reaction uh it is hard to derive the
laws of
friction but uh that's that's not for
tonight in any
case for
tonight we want to discuss en energy
conservation among other things we
already discussed energy conservation
several times but it's interesting to
see how these
equations from our from the present
perspective these now become the
equations of mechanics this is a new
formulation of mechanics based on H of P
andq given an H of P andq you now have
a phase space you have a motion through
the phase space
you can imagine dots in the phase space
a fluid of points in the phase space
moving each point with a velocity that
depends on its position according to
these equations and so it's a flow of a
fluid and it's simply a new way of
formulating mechanics let's forget about
all the old
ways oh I said I would work out for you
for uh for the ordinary particle let's
do that first ordinary particle again
mg^
2us U of X that's
the 12 and X do 2 now I replaced Q by
X okay oh we've done this before haven't
we what is it but I want to do I just
want to check these
equations okay so what is a handil we've
done that before everybody remember that
it's p^2
2N plus U of x
p^2 2N plus plus U of X is the hopon
let's just check Hamilton's equation is
d h by
DP differentiate that that's P Over
N that's what it is is p n equal to Q
dot or in other words is it equal to x
dot yes it is MX do is equal to P so the
first of Hamilton's equations d h by DP
is equal to Q dot that's nothing but the
definition of momentum in terms of
velocity and what about the other
equation d h by DX minus d h by
DX should equal p
dot the H by thex that's just du by
thex
us d by
DX that's equal to
P well that's just Newton's
equations mass time acceleration is
equal to
force so the second
equation typically the way it works is
the first equation is um the
relationship between position between
sorry velocity and
momentum okay it's just p m = x stop and
the simpli here it's the second equation
which really looks more like f = ma this
is masstimes acceleration and this is
force okay so it does work it is correct
it is
true and it is equivalent to all the
other
formulations we could work out some more
complicated examples and maybe we
will but first let's concentrate on in
this new form let's concentrate on
energy conservation let's see if we can
prove directly that energy is
conserned let's calculate the
HDT time derivative of the
hamiltonian if the hamiltonian is energy
which it is then it should be conserved
its time derivative should be zero let's
calculate it is equal
to the derivative of
H with respect to P time P
dot plus the derivative of
H with respect to
Q time Q
[Applause]
do su
I the change in h when you change P * P
dot plus the change in h when you change
Q Q do that's the change in hamiltonian
per unit time but now let's use
Hamilton's equations for p do and Q dot
what is p do p dot this is equal to some
I the H by d p of
I that's this what is p of I do can
somebody read it to me it's just a sign
that I don't remember that's minus so
minus DH by DQ
right and how about this one this is
plus DH by
DQ d h by D piece of
I and they
cancel that's what the minus sign is
doing
there is that equation if and only if so
if we have the conservation of energy we
get
equations
I think it's possible to imagine
equations which have a conservation of
energy which are not of the Hamilton
form uh if you have Hamilton's equations
I've with a Time independent Honan I've
assume the time I've assume there's no
explicit dependence on the honi of time
uh then you do get energy conservation
the other way no I think you can no you
can certainly have equations which have
conservation laws conservation of an
energy without them being of Hamilton's
form so it's not
if all right so we see that these two
terms simply cancel each
other and energy
conservation is a very very simp
consequence of
equations um it's kind of
interesting what this says is that if
you take a point and you follow it now
from now on I want you to think about
this phase space as a collection of
points that you can follow in
time as you follow them in time you stay
on a contour of constant energy imagine
this face space and imagine it being
filled with Contours of energy in other
words surfaces on which the energy is
constant it's simply filled up with
surfaces on which the energy is
constant the phase Point meaning a point
in this phase space as you follow it
stays on the same surface of constant
energy that's just energy conservation
the fluid flows the fluid defined by the
phas space dust think of it Dust In phas
Space flows along these
lines which are lines of constant energy
the lines of constant energy in general
can be close they don't have to look
like this they could be closed
curves for example we studied a case
last time called the harmonic oscillator
in which H was proportional to p^2 +
X2 let's let's let's forget the
constants it was just for getting the
constants it was essentially p^2 +
X2 so in that case the Contours of
constant energy were just circles around
the
origin The Contours can be open or off
to Infinity they can be closed curves
they can even be a
DOT that Corr responds to a motion which
doesn't go anywhere it just sits there
for example the harmonic oscillator
which has neither position which is at
the origin with no velocity it simply
sits there it doesn't move that's a kind
of degenerate Circle
uh right theology so the phase Point
moves on these surfaces this is very
much like the discrete situation where
you have different clothes
uh pieces of the face space and that
defines a conservation law which one of
the Cycles you're on call those Cycles
well in face space it's very similar
every point is on some Contour of
constant energy and you move along those
Contours yeah the density of points is
Conant we're going to we're going to
talk about that yeah the density of
points is constant how you get diverging
lines oh well that's easy actually we
haven't discussed the fact yet theity of
points is
constant um but let's let me answer your
question so
let's let's
imagine lines that look like
this
so the fluid comes in and goes through a
narrow
channel what happens when fluid goes
through a narrow
channel it moves
faster it moves faster just so that the
density doesn't change a big lump of
fluid comes in and it doesn't want to
change its volume so it has to squeeze
between these lines faster
lesson is where the where the lines
Clump up and get close where the conour
get close the fluid is moving
fast that's in fact what maxell's what
the Hamilton's equations
say when the Contours are close together
think about a contour map what does it
mean on a contour map that the Contours
are very close steep it's steep right it
means the altitude is changing very very
fast what does it mean on the Contours
of constant energy that the Contours are
very close together it means that H is
changing rapidly with respect to either
P or Q or some combination of p and Q
so where the lines Clump up is where the
H by DP and the H by DQ is large and
it's where the fluid is moving
fast so the lines can diverge all right
it's just the places where they diverge
like that the fluid slows
down and we're going to we're going to
study that behavior a little
bit have curves and
open what's that point you have closed
curves together with open absolutely let
me give you an
example the
pendulum and the
Pendulum
small oscillations at the bottom are
closed
curves the system just goes back and
forth back and forth Just Cycles over
the same uh and Define closed
curves the when it swings over the top
like this they sort of correspond to
open curves well let me let me give you
let's sit that there forget forget the
pulum take a particle that's
moving on a wash forward potential like
that potential which is just a sine wave
all right if you start down near the
bottom here and you give the particle a
little bit of energy all it does is
oscillate back and forth so it looks
like the harmonic oscillator in fact it
is a harmonic oscillator plus a little
bit of uh uh extra all right so it just
oscillates back and forth for and the
Contours are closed curves so for small
energy The Contours are closed curves
give it a big energy and it just goes
whistling off over the top of the
washboard if it has enough energy to
climb over the top and keep
going then the curves are open the
system doesn't come back to itself it
just keeps going off forever and ever so
yes you can certainly have uh both
closed and open C Curves in the same
face
BAS be interesting to try to I'm not
going to do it but be interesting to try
to plot what the Contours of constant
energy look like here on on the face
space any other
questions is there anything you want me
to go back
over
yes in general
generaliz is
pi always a Conant multiple of Qi Prime
say it again
do say it again extremely
clearly generalized coordinates
generalized coordinate yeah is pi always
a constant multiple of Qi do
no definitely
not uh it can no no no no not at all no
it's
just we can invent all sorts of
hamiltonians here's here's a hiltonium h
is equal instead of p² + Q ^2 let's take
P
cubed plus
uh X Cub instead of p^2 +
X2 this doesn't correspond to any uh
system that I know about in nature but
there's nothing wrong with it from the
point of view of the
hamiltonian now what are the equations
the equations are that derivative of H
with respect to P is equal to x dot and
that's 3
p^2 is equal to x
dot well that does not say that the
relation between p and x dot is that P
is a constant multiple of x dot so the
answer no not in
general other uh this is sort of unusual
but you could have an X here that would
be less unusual no sorry x * p^ 2 also x
* p is a occurs in hamoni but x * p²
then you will have the H by DP is um is
x * p and you would have p and
X the relationship between them having
an extra factor of X so no no there's no
reason for such a simple
relationship yeah it sounds like we're
describing sort of a perpetual motion of
of source really accur no well yeah
motion motion is
perpetual motion is
Perpetual that's why energy is
conservative but I'm not sure what
you're getting
at the idea that when you factor in
friction that you're
actually transferring the energy into
another part of the yeah okay
um before we can address the real
meaning of Perpetual and the pros and
cons of it and so forth we have to
understand something about
thermodynamics and we have to understand
the difference between usable and
non-usable energy and entropy and all
that sort of stuff so we're now at a
more basic
level uh studying the individual degrees
of freedom of a
system microscope for example if it's
this table with all the molecules moving
around in it so forth of the air in the
room these are are the equations that
really do govern the entire
system
uh in various kinds of approximations
you divide energy into usable energy or
available energy and unavailable energy
heat is unavailable energy but that's
got to do with the second law of
Thermodynamics which we haven't got to
yet I would hope to get to it it would
be nice to be able to get to it it's
deeply connected with these equations
and it's deeply connected with the
structure of motion in Phase space but
we're there
yet before we understand that
thermodynamics we have to understand
chaos and uh we are not ready to do that
tonight hopefully we'll get to
it
maybe okay so let's discuss
other conservation
laws energy is a conservation law that
follows just from Hamilton's equations
here there are other conservation laws
but let's look at the general form of
them we know from the leian point of
view that conservation laws have to do
with symmetries I'm going to suppress
that
now later on we'll come back to it and
discuss symmetries from the hamiltonian
point of view but now let's not worry
about why there might be a conservation
law just let's see what it means to have
a conservation
law what the necessary and sufficient
conditions for
conservation let's ask where the
quantity whether the quantity a is
conserved or not what is a a is a
function of
of the phase space wherever you are in
the phase space a has some value it's a
function of the P's and the q's or
equivalently a function of position and
velocity let me give you an example we
worked out a number of times ago that
the angular momentum of a particle
moving in a
plane is given by x * p y - y * PX it's
a function of the P's and the
q's General all quantities that we might
be interested in are functions of
positions and momentum if we know the
position and momentum of something we
know everything about it so in
particular we know the value of its
various quantities let's ask whether a
of p and
Q might be conserved might it be
conserved under what condition cons what
mathematical condition
now I want to express those conditions
in terms of Hamilton's
equations that's going to introduce for
us a new set of
quantities called quone brackets fish
brackets for those who don't speak
French okay this is easy all we want to
know is whether the time derivative of a
is zero on Mark in fact let's just
calculate the time derivative of
a d a by
DT let's just do root force will
calculate it's the derivative of
a with respect to P of I time P sub I
dot plus the derivative of a with
respect to to Q
subi * Q subi dot I'm going to write the
summation
sign explicitly now for a little while
summation of
I but now let's substitute in the P subi
Dot and Q subi dot their value in terms
of the
hemoc so this is some
I derivative of a with respect to the
pie of I what's piece of I got again
sign I can never remember the
sign it's minus
right minus
DH by DQ sub
I so we have d a by DP sub i d h by DQ
sub
I and what's this one this is
plus the a by DQ sub
i
q
that's the HTP
right well look at that that's kind of
interesting we find out that the time
derivative of any
quantity is given by the sum of two
terms let me start with this
one the a by DQ d h by
DP so if you know what a is and you also
know what the hamiltonian is you can
compute these things d a by DQ d h by DP
minus d by DP DH by
DQ a very symmetric looking construction
a very symmetric looking expression
mathematical expression that tells you
what the time derivative of a
is this mathematical construction let's
generalize it now take any two functions
of p and Q a of p and
Q and B of p and Q any
two how you get
lines then you define something called
the plus
bracket that's the symbol for the plus
bracket you take A and B put them inside
the bracket and put a comma between them
and that's the that's the symbol for the
plus bracket it's definition its
definition is sum of I of all the
coordinates the a by the
I
minus the a by the P of
i b by
bqi
you can see the symmetry of it it's
composed of two terms one in which a
gets differentiated with Q when b gets
differentiated with p and vice
versa that's called the Pome bracket of
A and
B we will see that another formulation
of classical mechanics is to write
everything in terms of these plus
brackets but here we are let's rewrite
this tells us that any qu the time
derivative of any
quantity any quantity at all whether
it's conserved or not in fact what I'm
talking about now is not conservation
but the time derivative of any quantity
and that's
equal the bracket of a with the
hamon person bracket of any quantity
with the honi is its time derivative
that's another formulation of mechanics
closely related to
hamilin if you're interested in whatever
it happens to be if you can express it
in terms of positions and momenta then
it's time derivative is given by the
plus braet with the hamiltonian the
hamiltonian is a special object which
generates velocity generates time
dependence by taking clome
brackets as I said this is another yet
another formulation of quantum mechanics
sorry classical mechanics me where the
motion of any quantity is expressed in
terms of plus own bracket with respect
to the
H let's just check it let's do one or
two
examples if you're like
this is a
generalization of Hamilton's equations
it includes Hamilton's equations for
example let's check Q
dot Q dot must be the plusone bracket of
Q with
h according to those equations let's see
what that says that
says one variable now one p and 1 q that
says DQ by
DQ d h by
DP minus DQ by
DP DH by
DQ I've now just substituted for a just
gr q q dot is the Pome bracket of Q with
h the Pome bracket of Q with h is the
qdq what's
that
one right so this is just one what's the
Q by DP
zero q and P are independent variables
this goes away and this just says that Q
do is DH by
DP no that's Hamilton's equations what
about P dot P dot is the plus
bracket of p with
h that's DP by
DQ
DH by
DP
minus the P by
DP the H by
DQ what's DP by
DQ zero and DP by
DP I think I just erased the minus sign
one so that's the other of Hamilton's
equations so the two Hamilton equations
are special cases of a much more general
rule that the time derivative of
anything is the Pome bracket of the
anything with the
hamon this gives a new view of
hamiltonians as generating time
dependence by the action of Pome
brackets the action of taking the
plusone bracket the hamiltonian tells
you how systems change with time that's
yet another representation of classical
mechanics
I think that's
probably Let's uh let's stop the
questions and not to go go any further
at this point is a carbon tax a
conservation law what's that is a carbon
tax a conservation
law
yeah oh well since I started talking
about conservation laws now we see that
it's a necessary and sufficient
condition to have a conservation law
that the quantity in question have zero
plus bracket with the
hamon now that may seem like an
incredibly abstract view of things and
it is but that's also a very powerful
and very general formulation if you want
to know whether something's
conserved you bracket it with a
hamiltonian and if it's zero then it's
conserved if it's not zero then whatever
it is gives you the time
der so um
try it out for angular momentum for
example try to take just a particle and
see what the angular momentum is
conserved by taking its plusone bracket
with p^2 over 2 m and so forth Let's uh
let's uh just take some questions now
and stop for the evening this I think
we' probably done enough for
tonight this is very abstract but it is
very powerful powerful means that it
that uh apart from the fact that you can
use it to calculate if you can more
important actually we haven't discussed
the fact yet that defens density of
points is Con not only the structure of
classical mechanics but Quant mechanics
reoccurs and reoccurs and reoccurs all
over the
place
yeah what's that how
did uh I really don't know
um I wouldn't be surprised if it came up
with it exactly this
way by calculating small changes and
things my guess is it came up with
exactly this
way
you why acking the chain
rule well we just found this structure
recurring in many context I mean you
know that's when uh uh now we're going
to study more General Plus brackets not
just with the heronian but between eight
pairs of
things
uh but you
know mathematicians good
mathematicians and theoretical
physicists people who tend to see
patterns they see the same thing a
couple of times and they say ah a
pattern I see a pattern and uh you saw
the same pattern occurring in a couple
of places and he said ah I'm going to
call it a key bracket
what are some other examples where B is
not
H we really got back to that oh what you
you're talking about the
non-conservation of energy right yeah
good
okay all right I have
assumed
that both the lran and the hamiltonian
Do Not explicitly depend on time now by
explicitly depend on time it means that
there's some time dependence above and
beyond the fact that the q's and the P's
or the q's and the Q dots depend on
time let's go and ask what
happens if the hamiltonian really does
depend on time how can that happen
dumping in energy right
yeah
but let's suppose there's a big lump of
matter over here our system is over
here we're not going to include this as
part of the mathematics of our system
but it exerts forces on
here and it's moving it moves from here
to here in a certain
way
that will mean the forces on this system
will depend on time in fact there will
be a turn in the energy let's just take
a single
particle there'll be AER the energy of
this particle U of its position which
also depends on the position of this big
lump but the position of the big lump
depends on time so that means the
potential energy depends on X and also
explicitly
time it means it depends on time even if
the particle doesn't move it certainly
depends on time just because X may
depend on time but that's an implicit
dependence on time there's also an
explicit dependence on time
corresponding to the fact that the uh
that the source of the um of the force
happens to be
moving all
right if the
hamiltonian depends explicitly on time
let's go back where
[Applause]
let's calculate P derivative of the
energy
itself this was our equation that we had
a few minutes ago and these two things
cancelled because P Dot and Q dot are
also derivatives of
H but it's just another term if h also
depends on T then we have to write that
the time derivative of H is d h by DP *
P do plus d h by DQ * Q do plus the
explicit derivative of H with respect to
T in other words the change in the Honan
even if p and Q are standing still if P
Dot and Q do are equal to
zero that's what happens if the
potential energy for example depends
explicitly on time
then this would of course be just du by
DT that's what it would
be all right so in that case even though
these two terms completely cancel each
other by virtue of Hon's equations
there's another term left over just the
explicit derivative of H with respect to
T and that's in general not zero it
won't be zero if the
Hamil it says what it says if the
hamiltonan explicitly depends on time
then that will appear in the equation
for the time derivative of the total
energy so that's as simple as that we
can uh we can we can do some examples
it's getting a little bit late I don't
want to do an example now but let's come
back to it an example of a a Time
dependent just a little definition in
the
bracket which which which is there a
convention in terms of which order there
is because there's a minus between
I hope my convention is the same as
plus I'm not sure it
is see I always Define it this
way a comma
B is the a by the
Q DB by
DP minus d a by
DP
DB by DQ and you know I don't think I've
ever looked that up to see but my
question was since you said it's General
general not just q's and P's being you
know these variables is it a of Q comma
P or a of P comma
Q as it just a mathematical
definition P or Q which is the first
which is the first VAR is a
second he said this is just an abstract
definition saying I don't think that
means anything um you can write it
either way I
mean uh
a oneus the
other could it
[Music]
be we could Define it by D by DP DB by
DQ minus the other one but this is the
way it's
defined it's not my that's not my
question is um since you said you have a
function a of p and Q okay does that
mean that Q is the
second are you taking the derivative of
a with respect to the first variable or
to the second variable in your in your
in your capital
letter which one is first and which one
is second you no no no no no there's no
first and second there p's and q's
that's all normally normally you put Q
position first before
momentum if you like but remember that
different you just to end up with one
one person one variation of
theet minus of
the if I write that the
hamian is p ^2 / 2
M
plus uh um one over
X Plus g m m over
X will you please tell me which is the
first one and which is the second
one it's just two
variables but it will reverse the sign
get a reversal
sign I'm never going to tell you whether
X is the first variable you know I don't
want to differentiate something in the
denominator please don't force me to
understand I understand when you mean I
understand when you mean momentum in
position that there's only one way of
saying it that's not my question you
said as an abstract mathematic you said
you said that this Plus on bracket's
going to come up in all kinds of places
so maybe that's not momentum in position
in which case it doesn't matter which is
which variable and I was wondering if
there was a definition that's all a con
as to the sign
of this particular structure doesn't
come up anywhere that I know of except
in in mechanics but um
but some people seem to be under the
impression that it's important to
describe whether X is the first variable
or the second variable it's not it's
just the X variable and P is the P
variable uh when I calculate the H by
the P I don't have to ask whether P
comes first and
XC and so forth
now you could have defined the quom
bracket in the opposite way in fact you
could have Define the hamiltonian with
the opposite sign all kinds of things we
could have done differently we made some
conventions this is one of the
conventions
um I don't know what else to say about
it let me answer your
question so
let's you're not
s the only question I had was pure
mathematical one you didn't know what P
was you didn't know what Q was it wasn't
momentum it wasn't position okay in
which case there is a difference of a
and the reason the only reason I asked
that is you said for brackets come up
all over the place and I didn't know
that it was always in the nature of
position and momentum or yeah I I don't
know any other place where brackets come
up uh except for positions and momentum
I uh what I did say comes up all all
over the place isre
Transformations LeAndre Transformations
do have this habit of coming up all over
the place the equations forand
Transformations don't have a funny minus
sign in
they read d
l by the V is equal to P the H by the p
is equal to V so in that particular case
uh there is
[Music]
no the preceding program is copyrighted
by Stanford University please visit us
at stanford.edu